[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
hello Sam how are you this is Frank de
Freitas
to talk to you
um
why don't we start off I know there's a
lot of information
on the website about the holography FAQ
or fact but maybe the listeners who
aren't familiar with it
or who have just accessed it to get
information and haven't read any history
about it maybe you could give us a
rundown of the history because I know
it's been on the web for a long time
[Applause]
well the uh my website has been up uh
since somewhere around 1994.
and start out from my uh
boredom at the
company I worked for which had taken
over a startup that I was involved in
initiating
and when it becomes a
big just become
so out of boredom I started exploring
the internet which of course at that
time was very very new absolutely in
1994 I don't even think it supported uh
photos did it if I remember correctly it
was just about
the Mosaic Mosaic came around yeah
that was the first browser I used
there may be
decent on my website in various places
yeah I haven't updated
that summer was mainly interested in
electronics repair and
started the
frequenting the use that news groups
groups and they're not there now
you know tens of thousands thousands at
that time they were
fewer but they were there were several
involved in technology uh one
particularly with
side not Electronics there that they
were
there were several electronic groups
bolt lasers that's alt lasers is a
fairly new group isn't it lasers
I don't know how
they were yeah
yeah relatively speaking relatively
at least they've probably been there for
10 years now yeah
So Silent chronic repair I I
replying to
carrying everything
from mowers
and that's how the electronics repair
fact side balance basically
Philip
whose last name I can't pronounce who
ran a website from Pittsburgh had some
informational Electronics but when he
saw all the replies I was providing he
asked if I would be interested
and uploading them to his website and uh
so that that began the development of
all the various uh repair manuals that
are up there now yeah basically I think
it started out more for repair than it
is than it was a a reference or a
resource right well it was
for repair yeah
later yeah
um
prior to that
aware of lasers since when they were
invented yeah but aside from using a
helium neon laser probably an early
metrologic in high school just to view
this file sign
hologram centerfold at that time
and various other little things with
lasers I really didn't do anything with
them around 1990 a friend of mine yeah
asked me why I didn't have it
I haven't so I couldn't because I let
that stand so I even ordered a couple of
helium neon lasers from SR plus
fire put them together I mean that was
just basically wiring a power supply
and like plugging it in and saying wow
okay as soon as my friend discovered
they wouldn't bring
lost interest I lost
I lost the shelf for a while for several
years we were seeing that all over again
now with the uh the one million watt
laser pointers that are modified the 1
million watt laser
that we don't realize what they're doing
yeah uh terawatt yeah
then a few years after starting the
repair website it would became apparent
that there were occasional questions but
Electronics news groups and the
responses from people who are usually
wrong
yeah that hasn't changed
so I started developing that and it
basically the the what the laser FAQ is
New Year's Day developed from an 18 to
a vial on how to safely power a laser
diet
player without blowing it up
and I have that in that actual file is
archived and linked from my my site
anybody really really has absolutely
positively nothing to do and they want
to look at that
what has that grown into today how many
web pages do you have total do you
happen to know offhand I have no no idea
I know I've been lost in there sometimes
at night oh I
get lost in there for months
you're a deity on the web when it comes
to lasers I mean people are just going
to fall over when they hear you on the
show I know it yeah
apparently doesn't job also because
almost any search on lasers will turn up
my link to my website in the top tens
what's the latest news on lasers I guess
the Green's the hot item right now huh
from the point of view of holographers I
think what has developed in the last
couple of years
is that I
put together a lot of information
which are the coherent compass
and the uh unified microgreen these are
both single mode single frequency
uh very long coherence Lane and
generally readily available Surplus for
well under a thousand dollars if you
know where to look yeah now that's more
than a helium neon but here we're
talking about
uh you know coherence lengths of
hundreds of meters mm-hmm
and I've heard
someone someone with baking Holograms
and with complaining that you know the
shelf in this Studio oh yeah
[Music]
I've I've heard of that happening with a
few regular laser pointers
the problem with laser pointer
yeah there's no real known way to select
a laser diode or to stabilize it
um
to such an extent that you can guarantee
that you'll have that the different
IO now it's manufactured the impurities
in it
so many so many
so many from a laser diode that change
characteristics
compared to even a diatom salt
and
they're the the train problem is that
the dogs really do like to run
multi-longitudinal mode so what you have
to do is temperature two
where it just happens to be running
single mode and you're lucky if you can
maintain that I mean as you're aware
that people do do make a very excellent
Holograms with
diets but they but they probably you
know cherish those laser diodes that
work well like that yeah I have one
that's been functioning for me since
I'd like to say 1999 or
2000 maybe I don't think it's a matter
of modern versus old I think it's just a
matter of getting one that happens to be
well yeah and then and then
happy would you recommend some people
going on to eBay what's I I haven't
purchased any lasers off of eBay but uh
what's your experience and what would
your recommendation be for people to buy
a laser Surplus on eBay or would you
have recommendations
what you're interested in knowing what
buying and
I've gotten most of my junk lasers on
eBay I mean I
I've probably bought you know somewhere
between
uh
lasers or laser items on eBay and I
basically had very few bad experiences
yeah but that
that one what I'm what what
what's being offered knowing what the
what it actually is not just going into
taking first laser that
that seems like it might be what you
want there are a lot of helium neon
lasers on eBay
there are a lot of Green Lasers on eBay
now but most of those are not suitable
for holography yeah they're multi-mode
either multi-trans mode or
multi-plusitudinal mode and a lot of
them are just in
yeah and that's becoming an issue now
having uh to order overseas and having
it shipped into the United States isn't
it or is that just generally with the
green pointers more so I think the green
pointers right now because of the
hysteria about the incidents with
airplanes yeah and uh I should comment
that most of that is totally hysteria
there's there's no way a green pointer
when he was going to Blind a pilot at 10
kind of legs they just have a life of
their own these stories and
unfortunately that may
work detriment of the
of the serious laser Community yeah over
time I fear that myself yeah the uh I
mean there's just so
just so information that that uh
just has no basis in reality
do you feel that the authorities know
the true answer
know the correct information or no doubt
it I think it's just
they don't have
really gotten expert an expert to
evaluate
yeah yeah
[Music]
certainly better for the better on the
side
but on the other hand
to say to suggest that
you know testing a green pointer normal
five millibar green pointer and shining
it up in the sky
and is causing retinal damage that's how
it's all I mean that's
that's the far way out of the left field
in terms of
specific
ations I understand totally what you're
saying and so do most of the listeners
well I had a guy that was out in Arizona
that I had written emails back and forth
to very early on when I was on the net
and he had some high power uh yag lasers
and one of their Hobbies was to bounce
it bounce it off the Retro reflectors on
the moon yeah just as you know fun I
guess that's totally over with you know
you know certainly don't want to get
caught doing that now well yeah
hurt anybody
[Music]
was a very difficult problem people
it's a parallel being light yet
the email at the Moon you've got a
reflection back there's some information
on the website somewhere about you know
how how many photons actually make it
back yeah and
you know yeah every so often you get
somebody emailing me or posting on all
about lasers you know I'd like to put an
advertisement on the moon I know don't
let's not get into the emails I'll tell
you I know but yeah the last week you've
looked at all about lasers there was
some guy who wanted to
hours or plants or something with a
laser and then he got got upset when
Pete said that's the
never dumb idea yeah yeah
there are always people asking a guy
caught along can I cut their ass at
night
yeah their applications for Insurance
where you're doing that but
suggests that it's going to be better
than a
true that's true there you go you offer
some equipment for sale or correct me if
I'm wrong on your website most of it is
[Music]
now is this functional equipment
non-functional well
it's certainly if it's
not this guy
oh sure but I wasn't sure which way it
was with what you were selling yeah
the
I don't have the Green Lasers because
I've not really gotten into buying those
for resale um
I'll pick up if they're cheap enough
they're available with
with power supply there's some assorted
diode lasers but mostly IR
for diet pump lasers program for the
do you know of any schools or
educational facilities that use your
website on a regular basis for teaching
there's this Stony Brook
okay laser teaching Center
[Music]
my website there's actually several I
can't can't
think of the others but you know they
they either they use the website or
their students
say well
because I have some you know rather some
helium neon Brewster laser tubes that
are useful for teaching you know where
you have an external mirror
there's no slavery student now I have a
spectrophysics 124 be stable light that
I need a tube for so do I do you
the two is a soft steel tube so at least
yeah yeah I mean there are lots of those
out there the lots of the uh the really
big one the
five which is
oh yeah
that's a Workhorse they're 127
for a couple hundred yeah
power supply but those are tend to
some of them are in mid
oh really about over 39 milliwatts wow
um that's hard sealed tubes in the 127
right it's a it's a sealed tube some of
them
either hard steel or yeah or something
something but a lot of them also a lot
of them have had two this week so you
can get stuck with something that might
be weak yeah
eBay I found probably in the 20
milliwatt range
the reasonably high power and stability
and everything it's just the power it's
not as high as it should be
careful about that though you get one
that's just no good at all yeah
but they they're available and they're
obviously they're the best helium neon
holography laser you can reasonably get
it recently
yeah
what um let me ask you this I don't
follow anything to do with any uh Blue
Wave once uh why don't you tell us a
little bit about the blue where it's at
where you see it going I know Sony or a
couple of the Japanese companies have
their d
players that's going to be coming out in
the blue
there are well they're two ways of
getting Regional power blue right now
they're popular one is the PFF laser
like
they're like except that
there's a different blazing line both
for for gag and for vanity they're
they're blue lines they're they're IR
line
[Music]
um vanity has nine
46.
which doubles to 450 seven which is a
very beautiful
blue
[Music]
a beautiful blue but it's so so close to
the uh
ultraviolet the visibility is is
several times lower than the heat okay
you need visibility so that's they don't
tend to use that a lot for laser shows
but I mean it would be good for for
Holograms probably if there's a film
then there's the
473 that's that's more like yeah
and it's about
a little less than a year
but as far as diode systems that would
be uh operational in single mode excuse
me again you don't
grading or something
or subtle mode you have the same problem
the red lasers okay combining it but but
obviously with
there are there are blue side lasers now
it's now 40 maybe maybe longer
wavelengths wealthies and power tens of
milliwatts 50 milliwatts they're the
Nicki Nicki guy might try diodes so they
have a whole range of diets from
near UV Beyond 400 to 440 or 450. yeah
of course you have to mortgage your
house to buy one oh my goodness I had to
take out a loan for my spectrophysics
when I got it from my lab that was 36
monthly payments it was almost like a
car payment for me back then I had three
three kids and
four pack
s what was the cause
oh the 124b I'm thinking
59.95 yeah I'm thinking that which was
believe it or not to me back then that
was that was a fortune well sure you
know
but fortunately things are uh
I've done some nice Holograms that
compare to the 124b with the um
a couple laser pointers now it's
incredible
well you know we must be neighbors
you don't have to sail in the air where
you're from
but we both have the same area code
yeah me too a little further up
Northwest of Philadelphia I am I was
born and raised in Philly yeah
well is there anything you want to add
to the show
I think everyone's going to love to hear
you on the show and of course we're
doing the podcasting now just got
involved with iTunes
eight years now for this broadcast so
this was it wasn't podcasting back then
but it was it was it was really early on
you know to do a talk show about
holography on the net when it started
eight years ago
but uh iTunes now you know everybody can
subscribe to it and have it
automatically update onto their iPods
and then go do what they want to do and
listen to it so that's a whole new realm
for uh
I don't know I have I have mixed uh
mixed feelings about it to tell you the
truth and um
uh one of the things that concerns me
about it is the fact that Apple's really
not investing anything in this how
that they'll give you a listing but uh
for their millions of subscribers
anybody who wants to listen to the show
your your data transmission is is your
own responsibility so you know that adds
one to your bandwidth and the amount of
data that you transfer you know to
people from iTunes
so for for no investment whatsoever you
know they're getting all the free shows
in there and plus um I don't know I
think just like with your website I
think anybody who's involved with this
field or has an interest in it probably
knows about this already so I don't know
what type of genre I'm going to be
pulling but we'll have to see there's
one of the problems I have with my
website is I often find people using
oh I yeah absolutely and uh I'll go
after them if they do that oh yeah if
they're if they're making money off okay
that would be fair to do sure go after
them yeah yeah you're not you're not
making any money directly off of it
that's for sure right
yeah oh absolutely yeah
same thing with me with the shows you
know yes yeah I like to do it I started
doing it I would be doing this whether
anybody was listening to it or not eight
years ago I just felt like talking about
it there was nobody to talk to so I put
a microphone in front of my mouth
said back then it wasn't as easy as easy
as now now it wasn't and it's been very
it's been expensive on occasions you
know whenever I do a show from England
before I got this new service some of
those shows cost over a hundred dollars
the phone bill my wife would open the
phone bill up and she'd say have you
seen this
you know so but now I have a good
service I think I get London now for
like 11 cents a minute or something
well Sam I want to thank you very much
for being on the show there's probably a
lot of questions that other people would
have asked you that I did not so I
apologize for that you can't get
everything
by the link in the link yes and I will
make sure that there is a link directly
to your web page for all the uh for all
the listeners and if you're listening
through iTunes
and you don't even know what website
this is coming from it's coming from
holoworld.com you'll see a link in the
iTunes directory go to the website go to
holotalk and you'll see uh Sam's link
and you can go right you know click on
that and go right over to it
Sam have a good rest of the evening
thank you very much for coming on the
show I know people are going to love it
okay okay take care bye